Guide to the Joseph Beckman Photographs of Long Lake Dam Construction 1910-1915
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Joseph Beckman Photographs of Long Lake Dam Construction
1910-1915
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
PC 135
Beckman, Joseph
.25 Linear Feet of Shelf Space 1 box 150 images
The collections consists of 150 photographs and postcards from the construction of Long Lake Dam, dating from approximately 1910-1914. Long Lake Dam is located approximately 25 miles northeast of Spokane, Washington on the Spokane River. Joseph Beckman worked on its construction.
Long Lake Dam is located approximately 25 miles northeast of Spokane, Washington on the Spokane River. This facility was believed to have the highest spillway (170 feet) and largest turbines in the world when it was finished in 1915 by the Washington Water Power Company, and is listed in the National Register of Historic Places. Long Lake, behind the dam, is also known today as Lake Spokane. Joseph Beckman worked on its construction.
The collections consists of approximately 150 photographs and postcards from the construction of Long Lake Dam (near Spokane, WA), dating from approximately 1910-1914. The majority of the images deal with the construction of the dam proper, though a small number deal with the worker's relaxation activities or with local natives. A very few images may deal with nearby Little Falls Dam. Also included in the collection is one two-page 1959 letter which serves as a brief biography of Beckman. The images are in no particular order. Approximately 90% of the images are labeled, but less than a fifth are dated.
This collection is open and available for research use.
This collection was received as MS 88-37 at WSU Libraries' Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections on September 16th, 1988 from Mrs. James Menzies (nee Marian Beckman). The photographs had apparently been compiled by Joseph "Joe" Carl Beckman, and his wife, Eunice Coffman Beckman (d. 1976-12-21).
The collection initially included approximately 50 additional photographs from WSC ca. 1910-1912, and a dozen or so pieces of ephemera or minor WSC publications. These were separated out, and interfiled into the Historical WSU Photographs Subject File (PC 2), ephemera collection, and appropriate places in the WSU Publications collection.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Beckman, Joseph -- Archives
Long Lake Dam (Wash.)
Public Works; Water and Water Rights; Washington (State)
- Man in front of house - D.B. Ludwick, 1912-09-01 (Item 1)
- Men on headgate 3 - Hans Anderson, A. O. Strauck, Jack Mintz, Joe Beckman, George Cowling, Joe Primiano (Item 2)
- High water running over temporary coffer dam in the canyon (Item 3)
- View looking upriver from head tower of #1 cableway (Item 4)
- Unknown building (not digitized) (Item 5)
- Men painting racks - Beckman (Item 6)
- Powerhouse, showing first steel columns and girders in place, October 1913 (Item 7)
- Excavation, 1912-11-29 (Item 8)
- Excavation Site for spillway dam, 1912-11-29 (Item 9)
- Front of spillway dam showing four undersluices discharging (Item 10)
- Temporary spillway (Item 11)
- View of arched cut-off dam from upstream side (Item 12)
- Headgate dam (Item 13)
- South side start of tunnel work, 1911-04-15 (Item 14)
- Construction from a distance (Item 15)
- Rock bottom of dam (Item 16)
- Broken Piers, 1914-04-08 (Item 17)
- Top of headgate dam (not digitized) (Item 18)
- View upstream from just above railroad bridge (not digitized) (Item 19)
- Cover house for coffer dam construction (not digitized) (Item 20)
- Looking east from tail tower (not digitized) (Item 21)
- Looking upstream from riverbank opposite club (not digitized) (Item 22)
- Powerlines to substation (Item 23)
- Cable Bridge (Item 24)
- Spud and Braggo - Little Falls (Item 25)
- Foundation (Item 26)
- Road at start of construction (Item 27)
- Cabins (Item 28)
- Aerial view of construction (Item 29)
- Native Americans and men (Item 30)
- View of generator room from switchyard gallery, 1914-10-14 (Item 31)
- Powerhouse construction (Item 32)
- Gage board, showing hand pump (Item 33)
- Location of gage board (Item 34)
- Taken at Long Lake, Aug 1913 (Item 35)
- View upriver from head towers (Item 36)
- Powerhouse Scaffolding (Item 37)
- Men on road (Item 38)
- Ross Park Steam Plant (Item 39)
- Baseball game - 3rd base line (Item 40)
- Headgate 3 (Item 41)
- Baseball game (Item 42)
- View of piers and spillway (Item 43)
- Men in village (Item 44)
- Right side of headgate dam (Item 45)
- Bartlett House (Item 46)
- Assembling of penstocks and sections after riveting, 1914-03-10 (Item 47)
- Bright day in powerhouse (Item 48)
- Two men at house (Item 49)
- Village (Item 50)
- Men by spillway during construction (Item 51)
- Looking downstream over headgate dam (Item 52)
- WSC group (Item 53)
- Clubhouse (Item 54)
- Pre-construction (Item 55)
- Tainter gates (Item 56)
- Looking upstream (Item 57)
- View of valley where dam now stands (Item 58)
- Penstock and men (Item 59)
- Four men (Item 60)
- Unknown man (Item 61)
- View of turbine room (Item 62)
- Water rheostat (Item 63)
- Steel distributing tower (Item 64)
- Camp, labeled 1-6 (Item 65)
- Spillway dam, Oct 1914 (Item 66)
- Native Americans on horseback (Item 67)
- Teepee (Item 68)
- Headgate operating mechanism (Item 69)
- View inside penstock (Item 70)
- Construction (Item 71)
- Tunnel to cable ways (Item 72)
- Pre-construction view (Item 73)
- Start of construction (Item 74)
- Coffer dam, labeled 1-4 (Item 75)
- Construction 1913, labeled a-d (Item 76)
- Cable towers and concrete boxes (Item 77)
- Concrete mixer (Item 77)
- LL Penstock Install Internal (Item 78)
- Headgates (Item 79)
- Construction, August 1913 (Item 80)
- Tunnel outlet just before closed (Item 81)
- Top view of early construction (Item 82)
- Penstock under construction (Item 83)
- Cement squares (Item 84)
- Construction from above (Item 85)
- The works (Item 86)
- Construction scaffolding, 1913 (Item 87)
- Gravel pit for excavation (Item 88)
- Scaffolds on spillway (Item 89)
- Tail tower of Unit 4 (Item 90)
- Unit 2 penstock (Item 91)
- Deflection dam (Item 92)
- Upstream view of construction (Item 93)
- Penstock sections (Item 94)
- Construction scaffolding, 1912-09-29 (Item 95)
- Headgate penstock install (Item 96)
- Looking upstream showing completed crest (Item 97)
- Labeled view of main dam (Item 98)
- View of rock bottom (Item 99)
- Looking upstream past broken pier in the spillway dam (Item 100)
- Arch cutoff dam (Item 101)
- View from bridge (Item 102)
- General view of power plant looking upriver (Item 103)
- Panorama, 1912-12-14 (Item 104)
- Spillway scaffolding (Item 105)
- Penstock construction, 11-18-1914 (Item 106)
- Generator install (Item 107)
- Spillway construction (Item 108)
- Penstock install (Item 109)
- Group at powerhouse (Item 110)
- Looking north, Long Lake Dam (Item 111)
- Steam shovel, 09-07 (Item 112)
- Dam from tail towers, 09-07-1913 (Item 113)
- Spillway (Item 114)
- Men and tent (Item 115)
- Headgate hoist (Item 116)
- Powerhouse construction labeled A-E (Item 117)
- Men by powerhouse (Item 118)
- Group photo: Long Lake construction (Item 119)
- Men in powerhouse (Item 119)
- Railroad construction (Item 120)
- Railroad and construction (Item 121)
- View of railroad and cables (Item 122)
- Powerhouse controls (Item 123)
- Entrance tunnel view (Item 124)
- Construction on rocks (Item 125)
- People labeled (Item 126)
- Head tower of no. 4 cableway (Item 127)
- Penstock towers (Item 128)
- Pitot tube (Item 129)
- Unit 1 erection (Item 130)
- Penstock entrance (Item 131)
- Tops of gates (Item 132)
- Headgate dam and inspection tunnel forms (Item 133)
- People touring (Item 134)
- Piezometer and bypass (Item 135)
- Vertical pitot tube (Item 136)
- Early construction (Item 137)
- Testing outfit (Item 138)
- Headgates labeled (Item 139)
- Looking upstream at dam, 1913-09-07 (Item 140)
- Men with powerhouse coils (Item 141)
- Bed of river with workers (Item 142)
- View of intake tunnel from river valley, 1911-10-30 (Item 143)
- Steam shovel and crew at gravel pit (Item 144)
- Generators (Item 145)
- Back of headgate dam (Item 146)
- Spillway and penstock construction (Item 147)
- Little Falls construction (Item 148)
- Unit one operation, Little Falls (Item 149)
- Post Street (Item 150)
- Letter (2 pages) (Item 151-152)